Which Side Are You On?
Harlan County U.S.A. is a documentary film directed by Barbara Kopple.
This film documents the coal miners' strike against the Brookside Mine of the
Eastover Mining Company in Harlan County, Kentucky in June, 1973.
Eastover's refusal to sign a contract (when the miners joined with the United Mine Workers of America) led to the strike, which lasted more than a
year and included violent battles between gun-toting company thugs/scabs and the picketing miners and their supportive women-folk.
Director Barbara Kopple puts the strike into perspective by giving us some background
on the historical plight of the miners and some history of the UMWA.
Preserved by the Academy Film Archive in partnership with
New York Women in Film & Television in 2004.
Self - Eastover Mining President, played by Norman Yarborough.
Self - UMW Organizer, played by Houston Elmore.
Self - UMW Staff, played by Phil Sparks.
Self, played by Bessie Lou Cornett Parker.
Self, played by Sudie Crusenberry.
Self, played by Mary Lou Fergerson.
Harlan County USA (variously written with and without a comma) is a 1976 American documentary film covering the "Brookside Strike", a 1973 effort of 180 coal
miners and their wives against the Duke Power Company-owned Eastover Coal Company's Brookside Mine and Prep Plant in Harlan County, southeast Kentucky.
It won the Academy Award for Best Documentary at the 49th Academy Awards.
It was directed and produced by filmmaker Barbara
Kopple, then early in her filmmaking career.
A former VISTA volunteer, she had worked on other documentaries,
especially as an advocate of workers' rights.
The film explores themes of strike, kentucky, mining, working class, union.
The tone is dark.